All right, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף *Daf* is י"ח *Yud
Ches* and the entire דף *Daf* will really be dealing with the
anatomical issues of the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* on י"ז עמוד ב' *Yud
Zayin Amud Beis* in which we left off yesterday. So actually we're
going to start, I really anticipate getting through all of י"ח *Yud
Ches* today, but we'll start very quickly at the top of י"ז
עמוד ב' *Yud Zayin Amud Beis* which we spent a few minutes
on yesterday, but we'll take it from the top. So let's look
at the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* on the top of י"ז עמוד ב'
*Yud Zayin Amud Beis*. משל משלו חכמים chachamim באשה: החדר, והפרוזדור, והעלייה
*Mashal mashlu chachamim b'isha: hacheder, ve'haprozdor, ve'ha'aliyah*. So the rabbis gave a
parable for a woman, for a woman's anatomy, and we spoke at
great length, a number of times, or not great length, but anyway,
a number of times about the idea of that the metaphor of
house used for a woman in different ways. So here in terms
of the woman's internal anatomy, the חדר Cheder *cheder*, the inner chamber,
the פרוזדור prozdor. *prozdor*, the antichamber, and the עלייה aliyah *aliyah*, the
second story. דם החדר טמא tamei. *Dam hacheder tamei*, the blood from
the חדר Cheder *cheder* is טמא tamei? *tamei*. דם העלייה טהור tahor.
*Dam ha'aliyah tahor*, the blood from the upper chamber is טהור Tahor.
*tahor*. נמצא בפרוזדור *Nimtza b'prozdor*, and if the blood is in this
third place, the antichamber, ספק טמא safek tamei *safeik tamei*, if there's
a doubt about where it came from, did it come from the
חדר Cheder *cheder*, did it come from the עלייה aliyah *aliyah*, the
doubt is ruled to be טמא tamei *tamei*. Why? לפי שחזקתו מן
המקור *Lefi she'chazkato min hamakor*, the assumption is that it came from
the מקור Makor, *makor*. Now notice מקור Makor. *makor* is a third
term. It's not, I mean not a third, a fourth, whatever term,
but it is not חדר Cheder *cheder*, פרוזדור prozdor *prozdor*, or עלייה
*aliyah*. It's מקור Makor? *makor*. Normally the assumption is, as they said,
is a different series of metaphors. It's about life and liquid and,
you know, the source of life and the wellspring and so on,
a very positive image for the womb. The assumption is is that
that refers to the חדר Cheder *cheder* and they're just different terms
because they come from a different collection of images. So I will
go back to modify that or suggest alternatives later, but let's start
with that assumption. So, let's actually then read first line of, well
actually I'll just say quickly, so we
assumed that the חדר Cheder, *cheder* here is the uterus, the מקור
Makor. *makor*, the פרוזדור Prozdor.
*prozdor* is the vaginal canal, the עלייה *aliyah* is this upper story.
We don't know exactly what it is, but actually the other tube
that's going on there is the urinary, what do you call, tract,
urethra, urinary tract as urethra is where it starts from. So that's
the עלייה *aliyah*. Now sometimes there could be blood in the urine,
so that could be a source of blood. Of course, and then
it says if you have blood coming from, the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*
is not difficult, it gets much more complicated in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. If you have blood coming from the urinary tract, it's טהור
Tahor, *tahor*. Blood coming from the מקור *makor*, the חדר Cheder *cheder*,
טמא tamei *tamei*. Any blood in the פרוזדור Prozdor, *prozdor*, in the
vaginal canal, is considered to be טמא tamei? *tamei* because we assume
it came from the uterus and it's uterine blood and it does
not have another source and therefore it's טמא tamei *tamei*. That is
very straightforward until we get to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that's going
to talk about a ברייתא *beraita* that's going to talk about a
connection, a tube, not a tube, whatever, some type of a, what
do you call those tubes inside the body? Tubes. Somebody help me,
Charlie. Anyway, whatever it is.
Charlie, wow. Anyway, whatever, anyway, something that connects those two. I want
to make one mention before we get into that which is תוספות
*Tosafot* makes an important point, which is you know there's a lot
of criteria in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about what constitutes דם נדה
niddah, *dam niddah*, color and other types of things. What's implicit here,
although not stated, but it's interesting that it's implicit and I've been
telling you from day one, is that one of the things that
constitutes דם נדה niddah *dam niddah* is that it's uterine blood. That's
the whole reason that דם מכה makah, *dam makka* is different, it's
not uterine. Well actually it does come from the uterus, but it's
the wall of the uterus, the lining of the uterus, or the
wall because there's a cut. So it has to be blood from
the uterus and from the lining of the uterus. It's implicit in
so many גמרות *Gemaras* where we talk about מקור מקומו טמא tamei
*makor mekomo tamei* like we just did, that clearly that that's the
source of the טמא Tumei, *tamei* blood and that's why דם *dam*
from the עלייה *aliyah*, whatever the עלייה *aliyah* is, is not a
problem. תוספות *Tosafot* just points that out, let's take a quick look
at the תוספות *Tosafot* on דם העלייה *dam ha'aliyah*. תוספות *Tosafot* says
משמע דדם העלייה טהור Tahor. *mashma de'dam ha'aliyah tahor*. No kidding. It
sounds like the blood of the עלייה *aliyah* is טהור Tahor *tahor*
אפילו הוא ממראי דמי טמאים *afilu hu mimarei d'mei tmei'im*, even if
it has the right color of טמא Tumei *tamei* blood, it doesn't
matter. And if you skip to the end of the תוספות *Tosafot*,
says how do we know that? והיינו טעמא דטהור דכתיב ממקור דמיה
*ve'hainu ta'ama de'tahor de'chtiv mimkor dameha*, the source of her blood, דוקא
דמי מקור *davka d'mei makor*, it has to be from the מקור
*makor*, from the source, from the uterus, דהיינו חדר Cheder, *de'hainu cheder*.
אי נמי דמים כתיב *i nami damim ktiv*, bloods multiple, מקום שמצויים
שם הרבה דמים *makom she'metzuyim sham harbe damim*, the place that is
the source of blood, that there's a lot of bloods in them,
a lot of colors of blood, ובעלייה ליתא אלא Ela, ממין אחד
*ub'aliyah leita ela mimin echad*, and from the עלייה *aliyah* really it
would come normally no blood, but if so it would be blood
of a cut, it would not be multiple colors of blood. So
that's important principle number one, that it's uterine blood and according to
the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, the only point is fine, uterine blood and
blood in the vaginal canal is probably uterine blood, end of story.
But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* makes this a little, quotes a ברייתא
*beraita* that makes it a little bit more complicated. Let's take a
look in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. רמי בר שמואל Rami bar Shmuel,
ורב יצחק בריה דרב יהודה תנו נדה niddah. דבי רב הונא Rav
Huna *Rami bar Shmuel ve'Rav Yitzchak brei de'Rav Yehuda tanu Niddah de'bei
Rav Huna*. They were learning נדה niddah, *Niddah* in the house of
רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna*. אשכחינו רבא בר רב הונא Rav
Huna, *Ashcheinu Rava bar Rav Huna*, Rava the son of Rav Huna
found
them, דיתבי וקאמרי *deyitvi ve'ka'amri*, they were sitting and saying, החדר מבפנים
והפרוזדור מבחוץ *hacheder mibifnim ve'haprozdor mibachutz*, the חדר Cheder *cheder* is inner
and the פרוזדור Prozdor. *prozdor* is outer. outer. So again we're going
to assume, if you look at the picture on the board, but
the חדר Cheder, we're going to assume for now is the uterus
is on the inside, vaginal canal is towards the outside of the
body, והעלייה בנויה על שתיהן, veha'aliyah benuyah al shetehen, the attic, the
second story is on top of both of them. We will again
now assume that that is the urinary tract. And now here comes
the thing that is not in the משנה. Mishna. הלול פתוח בין
עלייה לפרוזדור. halul patuach bein aliyah leprozdor. A לול lul can sometimes
refer to a chicken coop. Now a chicken coop is a tall
thin thing, right? So a I don't know now maybe they'll make
it differently, but anyway in the גמרא Gemara. a chicken coop is
sort of tall and thin. So basically it means some type of
a tract opens up from the עלייה to the פרוזדור. Prozdor, Now
there's of course a little problem because nothing connects, nothing connects in
humans. I'll talk about animals in a minute. Nothing connects the urinary
tract to the vaginal. As you know this goes into one orifice,
that goes into another orifice. There's nothing that connects the two.
We'll work with the גמרא Gemara and its assumption in a minute.
You know what, maybe I will say this moment
that Galen in Galen's anatomy humans have a tract that connects the
urinary tract to the vaginal canal because Galen did most of his
dissections based on cats and animals, cats and dogs
and animals. And in animals basically you have that. And in animals
you've got basically animals don't have by the way a vaginal canal
because they have the uterus opens straight to the
outside because animals have a lot of multiple births so they're all
in the uterus and it opens straight to the outside and they've
got their uterus here and they don't have two orifices and they
have their urinary tract opening into the sort of extended uterus and
then it all goes outside.
Okay so I don't know how that happens that the urine doesn't
infect the fetuses when they're gestating but that's not my problem now.
Anyway so that is you can take a look at that but
here this reality that
there's an עלייה a urinary tract
that opens into the פרוזדור Prozdor actually is true by animals and
that is a possibility about where this understanding came. We will again
deal with this for now and then I will give you some
alternative explanation.
The urinary tract that goes does go over the uterus?
Yeah and they both yeah but it opens up into a separate.
Let's say it's the way it really is, there's no לול. lul.
Correct, exactly.
It's all fine except for the לול. lul.
Okay so where is up? Then what do you mean up?
This would be the outside of the woman. Here's the back. Up,
back and front.
Which way is her head?
Her head is on top, okay.
Alright. Nobody
cares? No I want to
see which
one is the
uterus.
Alright alright I see, good point. Okay moving on. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
Alright so that's what they were saying. נמצא מן הלול ולפנים nimtza
min halul velifnim if it's found from the לול lul and towards
the inside meaning so it's
here right between the לול lul and towards the uterus, obviously it's
uterine blood.
So then מן הלול ולפנים min halul velifnim ספקו טמא sfeko tamei
if there's a doubt we assume it's טמא. Tumei, מן הלול ולחוץ
min halul velachutz from there towards the outside ספקו טהור sfeko tahor
if there's a doubt it's טהור. Tahor. Now that is very strange
because even ignoring the anatomical problems,
I mean the assumptions if it's from this point onwards maybe it's
from the urinary tract but certainly
it would be
very more
likely to be from the uterus.
I mean that's where normally blood is coming. So that is very
strange and I won't I'm just going to bracket that now because
I'll give you other explanations later but we're going to just work
with this explanation. So let's take a look. אתא ואמר ליה לאבוה
ata ve'amar lei le'avuha
so he the son of רב הונא Rav Huna here
רבה Rabbah told his father רב הונא Rav Huna this what they
were saying. ספקו טמא אמרת לן מר? sfeko tamei amrat lan mar?
Did you the master talking to his father did you say that
the rule was that it's doubtfully טמא? Tumei והנן שחזקתו מן המקור
תנינן vahanan shechazkato min hamakor teninan but I thought you said or
the משנה Mishna says וחזקה vechazakah is that it's from the uterus
which is more than it's doubt and we'll be stricter or whatever
weigh in and assume it's from the uterus. It's more that it's
definitely treated as from the uterus if it's from this point and
back.
So nobody is doubting that it is considered טמא Tumei. but how
much are you considering it to doubt and therefore טמא Tumei or
considering it definitely טמא?
Tumei. That's the question. So what's the answer?
אמר ליה אנן הכי קאמינא amar lei anan hachi kamina no no
here's what I said. מן הלול ולפנים ודאי טמא min halul velifnim
vadai tamei from that opening back towards the uterus definitely טמא Tumei?
of course what else is it except uterine blood. מהלול ולחוץ mehalul
velachutz from that point to the outside ספקו טמא sfeko tamei then
there's a little bit of a doubt and now it makes a
lot more sense we don't have to worry about the problem before.
Because there's a little bit of a doubt yeah maybe it's something
from that from the urinary tract maybe it's not uterine blood so
that's a ספק. safek. But nevertheless no because he said that's not
what I said, they misunderstood. Okay ספקו טמא sfeko tamei it's טמא
Tumei? so now it makes a lot more sense. Here it is
definitely טמא, Tumei. it's definitely, it's definitely uterine blood. Here there may
be some doubt, but nevertheless we are still going to rule that
it is טמא Tumei? because obviously most likely it is uterine blood.
You just repeat, who's talking to who?
So yes, רבה בר רב הונא, Rabba Bar Rav Huna, the son
of רב הונא, Rav Huna. it was רב הונא's Rav Huna ישיבה,
Yeshiva, maybe literally רב הונא's Rav Huna, ישיבה. Yeshiva. His son was
hearing some of the students talking over this discussion and they were
talking over what they had learned from רב הונא. And they had
learned that here it is doubtfully טמא, Tumei it is doubtfully טהור.
Tahor. רבה, Rabba, רב הונא's son, went to his father and said,
"How do you say doubtfully טמא Tumei? here? The משנה Mishna makes
it sound like it's definitely טמא." Tumei So his father was the
teacher, and he was recording what he had heard from the students.
And then the father said, "No, they didn't—either he was reversing himself
or he said they didn't understand, that wasn't what I said. What
I said was here it is definitely טמא Tumei. and here it
is doubtful but still טמא. Tumei So it winds up to a
more strict explanation because he heard back from his son what the
students were saying, his son challenged it and he gave a different
version."
They probably wouldn't necessarily be able to know, by the time you're
checking that deeply, it's the uterus.
No, that's not true, depending on the particular woman and so on.
It is,
this gets to discussions in the ראשונים Rishonim and the פוסקים, Poskim,
how deep do you have to do a בדיקה Bedika and have
to check.
But it's possible to get—anyway, depends where you think the לול Lul
is. You could certainly, depending where they thought the לול Lul was,
you could certainly get beyond the לול Lul in the front of
the לול Lul and so on. So let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. אביי Abaye says, "מאי שנא מן הלול ולחוץ
ספיקו טמא? Mai shna min ha-lul u-lechutz sfeiko tumei? Why are you
saying that from the לול Lul outward it's doubtful
טמא? Tamei, Because
דילמא שחצה ומחדר אתא? Dilma shachtza u-mechader ata? Now here again you
see a bias and an assumption that it's really more likely that
from this point on it is טהור, Tahor. like we assumed before.
And then why say doubtfully טמא? Tamei. But most likely it's just
from this point on it's—which again is strange, why? Again, you look
at this and it's clear that the whole thing is most likely
טמא. Tamei. But again, we will read that and then I will
give you an alternative explanation. So אביי Abaye says, 'Look, from the
לול Lul outside, it's most likely טהור. Tahor So why are you
saying we're going to be strict and say it's doubtfully טמא?' Tamei.
Because דילמא שחצה, Dilma shachtza, maybe she bent down, ומחדר אתא, u-mechader
ata, her body was configured in a funny way at one time
while she was bleeding, and therefore it's possible it came from the
חדר Cheder even though normally any blood there would definitely come from
the עליה, Aliyah, from the urinary tract and not been a problem.
Again, why we assume that's not clear. So if that's true that
you're worried about far-out concerns even though it's most likely טהור Tahor.
that blood, so even from the blood before, why do you say
definite? So מן הלול ולפנים נמי, Min ha-lul u-lefanim nami, so then
even from the לול Lul towards the uterus, backwards,
אימא איזדרקא מעליה? Eima izdarka mei-aliyah? Maybe she did a somersault or
a handstand and maybe it came back.
So he's saying from this point on it's most likely טהור. Tahor,
Why? I don't know. I'll give you an alternative explanation in a
minute. But from this point on it's also—it's most
likely from the עליה Aliyah and it's not a problem. But you're
going to say it's doubtfully טמא tamei. because maybe she did some
somersaults and the blood came there anyway from the uterus. So if
that's true, why are you calling the blood here definitely טמא? tamei,
It's possible that blood came from over here and went backwards, maybe
she did some other type of somersault and it came there. So
if you're concerned about who knows did the body do what it
normally did, then everything should be a doubt. אלא, one minute, אלא
אמר אביי, Ela amar Abaye, look, אי בתר חששא אזלת, Ei batar
chashasha azlat,
if you want to deal with maybe this, maybe that, maybe things
didn't do what they normally do, אידי ואידי ספיקו, Idi ve-idi sfeiko,
then both before the לול, Lul, after the לול, Lul, there's always
a certain element of doubt of where it came from, and therefore
we should say it's all טמא tamei, but it's doubtfully טמא. tamei
אי בתר חזקה אזלת, Ei batar chazaka azlat, but if you go
by the normal way the body behaves, so מן הלול ולפנים ודאי
טמא, Min ha-lul u-lefanim vadai tumei, from the לול Lul backwards is
definitely טמא Tamei, because obviously it's uterine blood, מן הלול ולחוץ ודאי
טהור, Min ha-lul u-lechutz vadai tahor, from the לול Lul outwards it
is definitely טהור. tahor, Now again you see an assumption that normally
from this point outwards it's definitely טהור. tahor. Why does this make
sense? It doesn't. The way I've described it, which is sort of
simplified, and we still don't know what a לול Lul is, you
still don't really know what this assumption is that this is normally
טהור tahor. because obviously the blood has to come out this way.
So I want to tell you what רש״י Rashi says. רש״י Rashi
says that the חדר Cheder, is not the uterus.
The חדר cheder, is not the uterus. But where is the uterus
according to רש״י? Rashi? According to רש״י, Rashi, the uterus is somewhere
down here. This is the uterus. Maybe according to רש״י, Rashi, this
is the מקור, now we know why it's called something else. Maybe
the חדר cheder, is the cervix, not exactly clear. That at least
makes it something else than the פרוזדור. Prozdor That's what רש״י Rashi
understands. But רש״י Rashi also Understand that's something else. Rashi understands that
there is, excuse me, that there is a different exit for the
blood. So what happens is the normal way the body works is
that the blood from the uterus comes—this is according
to Rashi or according to—?
Yeah, I don't actually let's back up a second. Okay, this is
according to Rashi. Okay, the blood from the uterus comes here, goes
into the חדר and comes out of the body. The
whatever this is, the עליה, Alia, let's call it the urinary tract,
this blood goes—I should use my other color, my other color—this blood
goes like this out of the body.
Not blood, this is the urine goes like that. There are different
exits, which by the way is good, because this goes to the—you
know, there are different exits out of the body. But the point
is that it's sort of like going in opposite directions. So now
we understand: any blood from this point on is definitely טהור. tahor
That's the assumption, because normally this is not the way uterine blood
goes. And any blood from this point back is טמא, Tamei. because
this is the pathway of the uterine blood. Okay, and therefore, so
as I said, this point back is טמא. Tamei, It is possible
she did a somersault and some of this dribbled this way or
she did a different type of somersault and some of it dribbled
that way, but basically they have different pathways and that's why you
can assume this way טהור, tahor, this way טמא. Tamei, Okay, so
making the human anatomy even more complicated, but that's what Rashi—But
how is it really?
What? How is it really? It really is is that uterus, vaginal
canal, urinary tract going to different orifices and we're done. Okay, there's
no point of connection.
So Rashi basically throws in one other part as—Well,
because it's actually not bad because the משנה Mishna speaks about חדר,
פרוזדור, Prozdor and then talks about מקור. Okay, but it still makes
the assumption of the anatomy even more difficult. Let me now tell
you what is probably the best explanation. It's not perfect, but it's
the best because it is possible that—and Rav Yaakov Lubba of the
ישיבה Yeshiva suggested this to me—there's a גמרא Gemara in חולין Chullin
that says that animals do not have a פרוזדור. Okay, humans have
a פרוזדור, animals do not. Now that might mean that they don't
really have like a separate vaginal canal like I said, it's all
big one big uterus. But the other thing animals do not have
as similar to the genitalia of humans, anybody know? Where our medical
doctors know? Okay, anyway, animals do not have external labia. Okay, and
if anybody knows—does anybody
know the medical term for—for
this space and the external labia of a woman? Hymen?
The medical term
is—anybody? Vestibule.
This space is
called—between the labia—called the vestibule. I'm fairly sure. Okay, so what it
could be saying is notice it says חדר מביפנים. Cheder mibifnim. Doesn't
that necessarily mean back with the מקור? חדר is internal, מביפנים mibifnim
internal, פרוזדור מביחוץ, Prozdor mibachutz, the פרוזדור is external. Very different explanation.
Okay, and if this is the עליה, Alia, the urinary tract, right,
and this is the vagina and there's a לול פתוח בין שניהם
Lul patuach bein sheneihem externally, right, so it's not internal, it's external.
So the question would be then if there is blood in this
לול Lul or somewhere in here, right, it most likely is blood
that came out of the urinary tract, right, because if it's blood
that came from the—from the, you know, from the
uterus and through the vagina, probably unless she's doing somersaults probably is
going downwards. Okay, so one way of reading this is that this
is the לול, Lul, this is the עליה, Alia, this is the
חדר, they are מביפנים, mibifnim, the לול Lul is מביחוץ. mibachutz. And
the question is
blood that is found between the two is חזקתו טהור chezkato tahor
because it probably came from the urinary tract unless she somersaulted, yes.
But no, there's no problem with the משנה. Mishna.
There's no—the משנה Mishnah, doesn't talk about the לול. Lul. Right, all
of this is in the גמרא. Gemara That is to—Wait, so this
is the same thing.
The מביפנים mibifnim and מביחוץ mibachutz are just interpreted differently, right?
There's the same thing. The woman's anatomy hasn't changed—No, no,
no, the חדר is still—no, they're not the same. The חדר, the
חדר's still the uterus—Right. The עליה Alia is still the—the urinary tract.
The big question is what is this לול? Lul? Okay, and the
פרו—no, what's first of all what's the פרוזדור?
No, no, the פרוזדור and the לול Lul are what's different.
The פרוזדור is the vestibule, the area on the outside.
Okay, and לול Lul is the space between the—you know, the—the opening
for this here and the opening for this. Does that actually—What?
It's not actually a track of any sort, it's just skin—It's a
space.
What? It's just space, whatever it is. It's a space, right.
Okay, but anyway by the way the משנה Mishnah: is also easy
because the משנה Mishnah. says, right, not if you have from the
חדר, anywhere internal here, it's definitely טמא. Tamei. Anywhere it comes definitely
from the internal— the urinary tract, it's definitely pure. If it's in
the פרוזדור *prozdor* and you don't know where it came from, you
have to assume it's טמא Tamei, *tamei*. Very simple, right? And then
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is just discussing what if it's in like
this space here, maybe there you can assume like חזקת טהור tahor.
*chazakas tahor* because and then the question is well, is she standing
normally, somersaulting, maybe it fell back or it's cancer so on. Exactly.
Exactly.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Where were we? Okay. Yeah. No, it's theoretical so I just, right.
Right,
bottom line is very little of this matters. If a woman has
blood, definitely came from her body, you know, internal check, even external,
definitely came from her body, she's a נדה *niddah* unless you have
a מכה *makkah* that you can, some you know, unless there's a
reason to have a basis to assume there's some medical problem that
was the cause of it. So yeah, this winds up being totally
theoretical. Okay.
All right, let's continue. Okay.
Where are we? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says תני רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya, *Tani Rebbe Chiya*. So רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya *Rebbe Chiya*
taught דם הנמצא בפרוזדור חייבין עליו ביאת מקדש ושורפין עליו את התרומה
*dam hanimtza baprozdor chayavin alav bi'at mikdash vesorfin alav es hatrumah*. So
the blood in the פרוזדור *prozdor*, again wherever this פרוזדור *prozdor* is,
which we are saying that there are areas, spaces of this פרוזדור
*prozdor* that are doubts and spaces that are definite. So he says
definite טמא Tamei. *tamei* and you would have to if the woman
entered or somebody touched the blood, the woman's a נדה *niddah*, somebody
touched the blood, he becomes טמא tamei. *tamei* and entered into the
בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, you transgress, bring a קרבן korban *korban*, no
question, definitely טמא tamei, *tamei*. If תרומה Terumah *terumah* was touched you
would burn it.
Isn't it even עזרת נשים *ezras nashim*?
No, no, no, the חיוב *chiyuv* for, that's true actually, a נדה
*niddah* and a זב וזבה *zav and zavah* or whatever are אסור
*assur* even on הר הבית *Har HaBayis*, so even before you get
into the עזרת נשים *ezras nashim*. Okay, we wouldn't bring the קרבן
*korban* till you entered the מקדש *mikdash*, but it's אסור *assur* even
on הר הבית *Har HaBayis*.
That's what I'm asking.
Yeah, but it could also be a man who touched the blood
or a man who touched the woman who is a נדה *niddah*.
But yes, even the עזרת נשים *ezras nashim* is forbidden as is
entering any part of הר הבית *Har HaBayis*. Okay, רב קטינא Rav
Katina, אמר *Rav Katina amar*, so you're definitely טמא tamei *tamei*. רב
קטינא *Rav Katina* says אין חייבין עליו על ביאת מקדש *ein chayavin
alav al bi'as mikdash*. No, you're only doubtfully טמא tamei, *tamei*. ואין
שורפין עליו את התרומה *ve'ein sorfin alav es hatrumah*, and you don't
burn the תרומה terumah, *terumah* because it's only doubtful. So here's exactly
the question: the blood here in this פרוזדור *prozdor*, whether this means
the, you know, the outside of the woman, you know, the vestibule,
or whether it means the vaginal canal. Is it definitely טמא tamei.
*tamei* or possibly טמא tamei. *tamei*? להך דאמר אביי Abaye, *Lehach d'amar
Abbaye*, according to the approach אביי Abaye *Abbaye* said אי בעית אימא
חוששא אזלא מסייע ליה *ibasya chushsha azlas mitsayeileh*, that if you go
by doubts, meaning that we should be concerned about doubtful possibilities even
not the normal way things happen. So therefore everything would be doubtfully
טמא tamei *tamei*, right? Because we always are concerned maybe it wasn't
exactly the normal way. So מסייע ליה לרב קטינא *mitsayeileh leRav Katina*,
that supports רב קטינא *Rav Katina* that says it's all this blood
is doubtful. ופליגא דרבי חייא *Upliga d'Rebbe Chiya*, and it argues on
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya *Rebbe Chiya*, because רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya. *Rebbe
Chiya* says some of this blood we would consider the woman and
the blood definitely טמא tamei *tamei*. So according to that, doesn't fit
with אביי Abaye *Abbaye*'s approach, אביי *Abbaye*'s possibility that we should always
be concerned with doubt. If we're always concerned with doubts and you
know and small possibilities then it's always doubtfully טמא tamei *tamei*. להך
דאמר אביי דאי בעית אימא חזקה chazaka, אזלא *Lehach d'amar Abbaye d'ibasya
chazakah azlas*, according to the other approach of אביי *Abbaye* that said
let's ignore doubts and go by the normal way the body behaves.
So the normal way the body behaves, is the blood in the
פרוזדור *prozdor* definitely טמא tamei *tamei* or not? So we said it
depends whether it's from the לול lul *lul* back or from the
לול lul *lul* forward. Okay, so let's try to see how this
fits. So according to the approach that we go by the normal
way the body works, מסייע ליה לרבי חייא *mitsayeileh leRebbe Chiya*, this
supports רבי חייא *Rebbe Chiya*. רבי חייא *Rebbe Chiya* says definitely טמא
tamei *tamei*. So at least the normal way the body works works
out there is some blood and he's definitely טמא tamei *tamei* מן
הלול ולפנים *min halul u'lifnim*, that works with רבי חייא *Rebbe Chiya*.
Okay. ופליגא דרב קטינא *Upliga d'Rav Katina*, it
one part of it argues on רב קטינא *Rav Katina*, which is,
you know, that this at least from this point back, רב קטינא
*Rav Katina* would never say that this רב קטינא *Rav Katina*'s one
who said doubtfully טמא tamei *tamei*. So he would never say that
from this point back it's doubtfully טמא tamei *tamei*, but this point
is definitely טמא tamei *tamei*. So at least רב קטינא *Rav Katina*
when he says doubtful would not be talking about that space. רב
הונא *Rav Huna*, according to רב הונא *Rav Huna*, remember what did
רב הונא *Rav Huna* say? רב הונא *Rav Huna* said that either
way, here or here, we're going to be, it's going to be,
רב הונא *Rav Huna* said this is אביי *Abbaye* said this is
where. Okay,
here's the לול lul *lul*. I'll do this simply even though we
worked out the problems, okay? Here's the point. So אביי *Abbaye* here,
אביי *Abbaye* said that this space, אביי *Abbaye* had two possibilities. אביי
*Abbaye* had two possibilities. אביי *Abbaye* said you go, if you go
by doubt,
then אביי *Abbaye* said this is all ספק safek ספק safek *safek
safek* because you're going by doubt so there's always a possibility something
is weird. If you go by normal, right, he said that
this is
ודאי טמא vaday tamei. *vadai tamei* and this is ודאי vaday *vadai*.
That's clear? Right, those are
the possibilities, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
now we have a debate that we just quoted that one says
ודאי vaday and one says ספק safek. in terms of the nature
of this blood, is it the woman's whatever. So we say according
to אביי, ספק safek would fit with the opinion that says ספק.
safek, According to אביי that says you look at the normal, okay,
then the one that says ספק safek has no space, has no
place here because if you say follow normal behavior, nothing is a
ספק, safek but at least the one that says ודאי vaday works
according to אביי that the space is ודאי טמא. vaday tamei, Okay.
According to רב הונא, actually,
there's an ability to say both the ודאי vaday position and the
ספק safek. position based on which side of the לול lul you're
on. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. רב הונא לא פליגי,
Rav Huna lo peligi, these two opinions of ודאי vaday. and ספק
safek, aren't debating. הא מן הלול ולפנים, ha mina lul u'lefanim, הא
מן הלול ולחוץ. ha mina lul u'lachutz. The one that says you're
ודאי טמא, vaday tamei? this blood is from the לול lul backwards.
The one that says you're ספק טמא safek tamei. is from the
לול lul forwards. Okay, very nice. Now, אלא לרמי בר שמואל לרבי
יצחק בריה דרבי יהודה, ella le-Rami bar Shmuel le-Rabbi Yitzchak berei de-Rabbi
Yehuda, remember the two that started the discussion. The two that started
the discussion, רמי בר שמואל, Shmuel right, they said, they said from
this point backwards, what did they say? ספק טמא. safek tamei. And
from this point forwards, ספק טהור. safek tahor. Right, remember that was
their opinion, that they called even this case a ספק. safek, So
there's no place for anybody to say ודאי. Vadai. According to their
way of reading, of ruling here, how does that fit with one
opinion that says that this woman could be ודאי טמא? vaday tamei
So according to them, דהוי מן הלול ולחוץ ספיקו טהור, de-avi minal
lul u'lachutz sefeiko tahor,
from the לול lul out to the outside is doubtfully טהור, tahor.
it’s a doubt but we’ll rule טהור. tahor. מן הלול ולפנים ספיקו
טמא, minal lul u'lefanim sefeiko tamei, from the לול lul. towards inwards
we assume that it is doubtful but we’ll rule טמא. tamei הא
דמאי מותקמה? ha de-mai motekmah? How do you explain this debate we
just quoted that according to one, according to רבי חייא, you're definitely
טמא, tamei and according to who was it, רב קטינא, you're ספק
טמא. safek tamei So how do you work it? So there's one
opinion that works, the ספק טמא safek tamei opinion can work. But
the opinion that says ודאי טמא vaday tamei. cannot find any place
within this read of the משנה. Mishnah: So מן הלול ולפנים לימא
פליגי דרבי חייא? minal lul u'lefanim leima peligi de-Rabbi Chiya? So let's
say from the לול inwards, at least the ספק טמא safek tamei,
decision works, but there was a position of
רבי חייא that called this blood ודאי טמא. vaday tamei So it
seems that there's no way that רבי חייא can fit within their
position.
So maybe it argues on רבי חייא. So it says, לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן כשנמצא בקרקע פרוזדור וכאן כשנמצא בגג
פרוזדור. kan keshenimtza bekarka prozdor ve-kan keshenimtza begag prozdor.
Now we’re going to have another consideration. The blood from the חדר,
which is טמא, tamei runs on the floor. If it came from
the לול somehow, if
there's blood, it will be not on the floor but most likely
on the גג. gag. Okay, exactly how you find it exactly this
precisely is unclear. So where did they say ספק safek. טמא, tamei
okay, that is if it is over here, if it’s on the
גג, gag, it is then there’s a reason to really say it
came from the לול. Okay, I said it wrong, the other way.
But they would agree that if it was on the floor of
the here, then that is definitely from the חדר, so they can
also hold that there is a space that is ודאי טמא Vadai
tamei if it is not on the גג gag but if it
is on the קרקע. karka. And with that we are done with
the woman's anatomy and all the different positions. So let us move
on.
Okay,
fine. Now we go on. אמר רבי יוחנן בשלשה מקומות הלכו חכמים
אחר הרוב. amar Rabbi Yochanan beshlosha mekomot halkhu chachamim achar harov. We
don't know how to
rule at this point yet,
but it doesn't really matter as we’re saying. Yeah, blood that definitely
comes from the woman is
טמא tamei unless you have a מכה, end of story. Okay, moving
on. And now the גמרא Gemara says like this. בשלשה מקומות הלכו
חכמים אחר הרוב. beshlosha mekomot halkhu chachamim achar harov.
In three places the rabbis went by majority. ועשאום כודאי, va’asuum kevaday,
and treated it like definite. Now the funny thing is, what do
you mean three places? I mean there's always a rule that you
go by majority, so the basic point is yes, but it’s a
very fascinating question when we rule by רוב, rov, how much do
we rule by רוב rov and like say that we acknowledge there’s
a problem but we’re assuming it’s the רוב, rov, and how much
do we say it’s like there’s not even any question at all?
So it’s definitely okay. And like would there ever be a reason
to still be concerned about the small possibility that maybe maybe you
know it’s not like the רוב. rov. So here it’s saying that
there are three places, of course the גמרא Gemara is going to
say there are many more, but emphasizing three places where we say
it’s as if it's definite, as if there’s no question. What are
those three places? And
you'll see
there. They are all obviously within the theme of טומאה וטהרה Tumah
v'Taharah and a woman, okay? And in those places there are three
cases, the גמרא's Gemara going to say that in a minute, three
cases of where we treat a רוב Rov as if it's a
definite, a majority as a definite. ונחזי, V'nechezi, let's analyze, we're going
to analyze. מקור המטמא, Makor Hametamei, the uterus like we said, that
when there's blood in at least some place here, it's definitely טמא,
even though there's always a little bit of a doubt. We're going
to rule that there's places, you know, when it's from the לול
לפנים Lul Lifnim etc., it's definitely טמא. We treat it as definite.
And definite means what? That's a ודאי. Vadai Whichever way you find
a ודאי vadai there, and that definite, the point of that definite
is for example, she can definitely start counting her seven days from
that day. You don't, it's not just being strict and considering it
טמא, if it's a question of establishing her וסת, Veset, she assumes
she definitely saw then. So we treat it as definite. Not we're
doubtful but we're strict, so it's definite. That's our משנה, mishnah: the
מקור. שליה, Shilya, what about the case about the embryonic sac? שליה
דתנן, Shilya detnan, we taught in the משנה: Mishnah שליה בבית הבית
טמא. Shilya babayit habayit tamei. If there is a שליה Shilya in
a house, then the house is טמא, because meaning of מת, Mes,
because obviously there's a miscarried fetus.
An actual house now.
In the actual house, thank you. Right, because of the
concern about the miscarried fetus and therefore it's all, it's
טומאת מת. Tumas Mes. Of a corpse, anything in the house is
טמא. ולא שהשליה ולד, V'lo shehashilya velad, it's not that this is
actually a fetus itself, אלא שאין שליה בלא ולד, ela she'ein shilya
belo velad, but you don't have one without there being a fetus.
So even if you can't find the fetus, it's possible probably that
it's somehow mixed up in the embryonic fluids within the sac and
you can't exactly identify it, but nevertheless there's a fetus there and
everything.
So you notice it wasn't a live birth. Otherwise you could say,
just go to the house...
No, no, no, no, no. It's a miscarriage, it's a miscarriage. Okay?
And that's why we say it is ודאי vadai? טמא and not
just doubtful. It says here it's definite, definitely there was a fetus
there. רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, I mean I guess the נפקא מינה
Nafka mina about it, well I'm trying to think about a נפקא
מינה, Nafka mina, חייבין עליו על שריפת תרומה, chayavin alav al sereifat
terumah, if somebody then touched תרומה terumah it would be a proof
that it's definite and not doubtful. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer,
Rabbi Shimon says no, it's not definite, נימוק הולד עד שלא יצא,
nimok havelad ad shelo yatza, maybe the fetus dissolved before it came
out of the woman's body, and maybe there is no fetus in
the embryonic sac, and therefore it's not definitely טמא, it is only
doubtfully טמא. Okay, that is, okay,
so other than Rabbi Shimon, where we treat it as if it's
definite, even though there maybe is a basis for doubt. חתיכה, Chaticha,
how about a chunk? דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה. Mishnah
Notice by the way that all of these are משניות Mishnayos as
well, דתנן דתנן דתנן. detnan detnan detnan. We taught in the משנה:
המפלת יד חתוכה. hamapelet yad chatucha.
If a woman miscarries and what comes out is a little hand
that is חתוכה, Chatucha, it does not mean chopped off, it means
that it is the fingers are divided. Okay? So it's already to
the point
that it is
the fingers are distinguished and divided, so it's developed. So in that
case, רגל חתוכה regel chatucha or similarly by a leg where the
toes would be divided, אמו טמאה לידה. imo tmeia leida. The mother
is considered to have given childbirth. It's not a case of a
מת, Mes, of a corpse, because it's only a part of the
body and so on and maybe it, but
anyway we're not going to worry right now about the corpse issue.
I mean obviously by טומאת מת Tumas Mes it also goes by
a part of the body. So anyway, what we're not worrying about
the corpse issue, we're worrying about the mother. Is she considered a
יולדת? Yoledet? So we say she is. Now why is there an
issue? Because if a mother miscarries she has the טומאה Tumah of
a יולדת. Yoledet. But if it is a child that was never
developed, not just a miscarriage but to some degree would never have
been considered to have been, it'd be a whole פרק Perek devoted
to that, somehow like not even a human birth or not, you
know, something that was considered to have never
actually had a certain stage of development or even normal development,
then that would be, she would not be considered a יולדת. Yoledet.
But a miscarriage is definitely יולדת, Yoledet, but cases where the fetus
has developed in strange ways, it's possible it would not. So here
you don't know how the rest of the fetus developed. All you
see is one limb. But obviously if that one limb looks properly
developed, you can assume that the fetus was developing properly and therefore
even if she did not have a chance to inspect the rest
of what the miscarriage, she has to assume that it was a
normally developing fetus and that she is טמאה לידה. tmeia leida.
Doesn't this go by time?
Less than 40 days is definitely not a problem, but even more
than 40 days it's not just hasn't developed enough but if it's
also not a type of a normal development. So you're right, less
than 40 days she would not be טמאה לידה, tmeia leida, but
even more than there
are...
Is there halachic literature on what constitutes development?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, well there's a whole what? You mean how the
development? There's a whole פרק perek devoted to the fetal development issue
and later so we'll get to it. All right, so it says
הרי זו חתיכה, Harei zu chaticha, אמו טמאה לידה, imo tmeiah leida,
the mother is considered to have the טומאה tumah of childbirth, ואין
חוששין שמא מגוף אטום בא, v'ein chosheshin shema miguf atum ba, and
you're not concerned that it came from a body that literally is
sort of like, you know, like a block, a body that had
never developed into the various, you know, the various limbs and so
on. If one limb was developed, you assume the fetus was developing
naturally and therefore it is a miscarriage that creates טומאת לידה. tumah
leida. Okay, so that's another case, but is there a possibility? Sure,
there's a possibility otherwise, but nevertheless, we treat it as ודאי vadai,
based on the evidence. The גמרא Gemara asks ולמאן דאמר u'l'man d'amar
do we know of the cases that we go by majority and
treat it as ודאי? vadai והאיכא, V'ha ika, how about the case
of תשע חנויות tesha chanuyot of nine stores? דתניא, D'tanya, okay, תשע
חנויות tesha chanuyot כלן מוכרות בשר שחוטה, kulan mochorot basar shechuta, nine
stores are all selling kosher meat, slaughtered meat, ואחת מוכרת בשר נבלה
v'achat mocheret basar neveila and one is selling נבלה neveila meat. לקח
מאחת מהן Lakach me'achat mehen and somebody purchased from one store. And
then he then forgets which store that they went into. ספקו אסור,
Sfeiko assur, we rule it's forbidden. Why? Not just we're being strict,
but there's a general principle that you don't go by רוב rov
when things are קבוע. kavua. When the sort of sources of when
you have something and you're trying to identify where it came from
and everything has a fixed place. There are like nine things, ten
things here, one is good and nine are not good or vice
versa and you pick them up and they're all somehow fixed from
their place, then that is a principle of כל קבוע, kol kavua,
anything fixed you treat as if it's כמחצה על מחצה, k'mechtza al
mechtza, fifty-fifty. If however you did not remove it from its place
but one thing, you found one thing here and you want to
know which, where did it come from? You were not, did not
go to it in its fixed place with the other things, then
you say you assume it came from the majority. Now obviously percentage-wise,
probability, it doesn't matter, but you have to understand and I'm not
going to get into a discussion about this here, this is being
brought up only incidentally, that somehow the idea is when I go
to where it's קבוע, kavua, then there is the I'm definitely engaging
in the reality of the problematic thing or the other thing, whether
the other thing is the good or the bad thing, right? So
there's a good thing here, there's a bad thing here, that is
a present possibility and I can't ignore that. It's sort of like
what we learned by pieces of שתי חתיכות. shtei chatichot. When it's
a present possibility, then that you have to be addressed and that
creates it like fifty-fifty. When I find one piece over here, it's
an abstract question: what is the identity of this one thing? So
that question I go by majority. But here when I'm encountering the
things, then I have to treat it as fifty-fifty. That's the rule.
So the person went to the stores and in front all the
stores are there and he doesn't know which store, so sort of
like he's thinking in his mind there are ten stores, which one
did I go to? So they're all in front of him and
he took from one of them and that's קבוע kavua and that's
fifty-fifty and therefore you're strict. ובנמצא, Uv'nimtza, but if you found a
piece of meat on the ground, הלך אחר הרוב, halech achar harov,
so the most likely it was kosher and that's okay. So therefore,
my God, you're going to eat this piece of meat! So you're
going by a majority. Now again, what it really boils down to
is the הלכה halacha that you go by majority, which is what
the גמרא Gemara is asking. What do you mean? Three places we
go by רוב? rov? I mean look, we go by רוב, rov,
we let you eat a piece of meat, we're not concerned it's
נבלה, neveila, so we do it all the time! So the גמרא
Gemara says like
this: טומאה קאמרינן, איסורא לא קאמרינן. tuma kaamrinan, issura lo kaamrinan. No,
no, of course in plenty of places we go by רוב. rov.
We're talking about in the world of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'tahara. The
גמרא says, so what? Have we other cases of טומאה וטהרה? tumah
v'tahara? והאיכא, V'ha ika, how about this case? Just like the stores
except with frogs. תשעה צפרדעים, tisha tzfardeim, nine frogs, frogs are do
not transmit טומאה tumah when they are dead, ושרץ אחד, v'sheretz echad,
one dead rodent that transmits טומאה, tumah, ביניהם, beineichem, if they so
there's a pile of dead things, frogs and rodents, ונגע באחד מהן,
v'naga b'echad mehen, you touched one of them, ואינו יודע באיזה מהן
נגע, v'eino yodeia b'eizeh mehen naga, you don't know which one. So
again, it's you're dealing with them where they are fixed, it's like
it's fifty-fifty. So what do you do at fifty-fifty? So by טומאה
tumah you don't restrict, it depends where it happened. Private domain, public
domain, things we've been talking about. ברשות היחיד ספקו טמא, B'reshut hayachid
sfeiko tamei, if this happened in a private domain, so a fifty-fifty
doubt you rule that it's טמא. ברשות הרבים ספקו טהור, B'reshut harabim
sfeiko tahor, if it's in a public domain, you rule leniently, it
is טהור. tahor ובנמצא, Uv'nimtza, but if it wasn't a mixed pile
of stuff, you touched one thing that came from the pile, you
don't know what you touched, you weren't paying attention, then it goes
by the רוב, rov, by the abstract possibility of probability of what
it is. So you touched one, it was separated from the pile,
הלך אחר הרוב, halech achar harov, you go by the majority. And
here you really do see ודאי, vadai. because even if it's in
a private domain, you're lenient. Normally the rule is in a private
domain we're always strict, but here we assume we go by probability,
we assume its identity was based on the probability on the רוב
rov and we assume it was definitely
the identity, let's say the frog, and therefore definitely טהור tahor even
in a private domain. So you see by טומאה וטהרה tumah v'tahara
we also in general we hold of this rule you go by
majority and we treat it as definite, not as doubt. And here
again it's important the idea of it's not just we rule by
רוב rov like the piece
of— Okay fine we say it in other places of טומאה וטהרה
tumah vetaharah *tum'ah v'taharah* as well. But אשתכח מינן *ishtakach minan* we're
talking about the world of טומאה tumah וטהרה *tum'ah v'taharah* with women's
cases, cases involving women, there we have three cases that are we
go by רוב rov *rov* and we treat it as a ודאי
vadai *v'adai*. So טומאה tumah בעלמא לא קאמרינן *tum'ah b'alma lo ka'amrinan*
not just general טומאה וטהרה *tum'ah v'taharah*. Gemara says one minute I'll
give you another case. והא איכא הא דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי
*v'ha ika ha d'amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi*. Have a רבי יהושע
בן לוי *Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi* as another case about women in
טומאה וטהרה *tum'ah v'taharah*. עוברת בנהר *overet b'nahar* a pregnant woman walks
through a river והפילה *v'hipilah* and she miscarries. Now the question is
she can't see the fetus because it fell out in the river.
So she has to know, right, was the fetus developed enough
to make her a יולדת yoledes *yoledet* or not? So what is
her status? Does she is she considered a definite woman who has
childbirth that she's טמאה tmeiah *t'meiah*, טמאה tmeiah *t'meiah* that she brings
a קרבן *korban* and so on. So he says מביאה קרבן ונאכל
*m'via korban v'ne'echal*. She's definitely טמאה tmeiah *t'meiah* she brings a קרבן
*korban* and the proof that we treat her as definite is you
can eat the קרבן *korban*. If she would only have brought the
קרבן *korban* on doubt because it's a bird and you do the
מליקה *melikah* from the back of the head and the whole thing
you would not have eaten the קרבן *korban* based on the doubt
but the fact that she's bringing it and eating it proves we
treat it as definite because most women who are pregnant they are
have a properly developed fetus and therefore even though we don't know
we treat it as definite based on the majority. הלכה אחר הרוב
*halachah achar harov* we go by the majority רוב rov נשים *rov
nashim* most women. ורוב נשים ולד מעליא ילדן *v'rov nashim velad malya
yaldan* most women give birth to a properly developed fetus even if
it's a miscarriage the fetus is still properly developed and therefore she
still has the טומאה *tum'ah* of a יולדת yoledes *yoledet*.
This was in those days apparently.
Well they had a lot of miscarriages but it doesn't mean that
they had very strange fetal development. Okay yes. Alright so now it
continues. So Gemara says ah you see you have another case about
women. So the Gemara and טומאה *tum'ah*. So the Gemara says מתניתין
קאמרינן שמעתא לא קאמרינן *matnitin ka'amrinan shem'ata lo ka'amrinan*. We're talking about
משניות *mishnayot*. In the משניות *mishnayot* that deal with טומאה וטהרה *tum'ah
v'taharah* about women there are three cases of going by רוב rov
*rov* and treating it like ודאי vaday, *v'adai*. Which is true that
is common to all of those three. So obviously there's רוב rov
*rov* throughout all of ש"ס Shas *Shas*. So Gemara says wait I'll
give you another משנה *mishnah* about women. והא כי אתא רבין אמר
*v'ha ki ata Ravin amar* when רבין *Ravin* came he said מותיב
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא טועה *motiv Rabi Yosi b'rebi Chanina to'ah*. So
this is alluding to a whole other גמרא *Gemara* and we're only
alluding to it we're not going to discuss it even רש"י *Rashi*
doesn't discuss it. So he said רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא *Rabi Yosi
b'rebi Chanina* asked regarding the case of טועה *to'ah* a woman who
is not sure when exactly her period is and then and he
asked from this case about the woman who is miscarrying that we
just said in the river. And
and he said and רבין *Ravin* said ולא ידאנה מאי תיובתיה *v'lo
yadana mai tiuvteih* I didn't know what was bothering him. So the
Gemara says well let me just check רש"י *Rashi* one second hold
on. No
I'm sorry one second alright I thought I missed that I'm sorry
I thought I missed that. So רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabi Yehoshua
ben Levi*'s פסק *psak* about miscarriage so רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא *Rabi
Yosi b'rebi Chanina* asked a challenge that פסק *psak* about miscarriage in
the river that we just read from a ruling about a woman
that had missed her cycle. He had a whole case about a
woman who had missed her cycle a משנה *mishnah* about a woman
who did not know her cycle. He used that משנה *mishnah* to
challenge this פסק *psak* about the woman passing through the river. That's
all you need to know. We have this case about the woman
and the river and miscarriage and this and רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא
*Rabi Yosi b'rebi Chanina* challenged it with using a משנה *mishnah* about
a woman who did not know when her period was when her
cycle was. And then רבין *Ravin* said ולא ידאנה מאי תיובתיה *v'lo
yadana mai tiuvteih* I didn't understand why that משנה *mishnah* was a
challenge. So the Gemara says it's very funny how this is you'll
see what's doing with all of this. מאי לאו לא תיובתא אלא
סייעתא *mai lav lo tiuvta ela say'ata* when he said I didn't
understand why that משנה *mishnah* was a challenge to this position of
the woman in the river didn't he did he not mean I
didn't understand why it was a challenge and actually it's the opposite
that משנה *mishnah* is a support of the woman in the river?
So we're trying to based on this we're trying to say ah
you see based on a whole other discussion we have it sounds
like there was a משנה *mishnah* that supported this case of the
woman in the river. So therefore there's another case based on a
משנה *mishnah*. This whole case of woman in the river that you
said isn't relevant because it's not based on a משנה *mishnah*. Oh
it sounds like from another discussion there is a משנה *mishnah* that
supports it so therefore it's relevant to our discussion. So Gemara says
no give me a break. The Gemara says לא מאי לאו לא
תיובתא ולא סייעתא *lo mai lav lo tiuvta v'lo say'ata* that other
משנה *mishnah* wasn't a challenge but it wasn't a support. So bottom
line we're done with what we said there are three cases in
the משניות *mishnayot* dealing with women dealing with טומאה וטהרה *tum'ah v'taharah*
where we go by רוב rov, *rov* and treat it like ודאי
*v'adai*. So now the Gemara says alright why did you bother saying
that we always go by רוב rov *rov*. So the Gemara says
למעוטי מאי *l'ma'utei mai* what are you trying to exclude meaning if
you're emphasizing three it sounds like you're saying not every case. So
which case would not be that. So אילימא למעוטי רובא דאיכא חזקה
chazaka, בהדיה *elima l'ma'utei ruba d'ika chazaka bahadeih* here's a very fascinating
question which goes alludes back to another discussion we had. What happens
if רוב rov *rov* is against חזקה chazaka, *chazaka*? Who wins? חזקה
chazaka, *chazaka*. Status quo, רוב rov? is majority, who's gonna win? So
that's the question right in the beginning of חולין, Chullin, רוב וחזקה,
דהי עדיף? rov ve'chazaka, de'hay adif? And the conclusion of that גמרא
is, רובא עדיף, rova adif, רוב rov wins. Now, you might actually
have remembered an earlier discussion that we had which used different terms
but was a similar question: ספק מוציא מידי ודאי? safeik motzi mi'dei
vadai? If something had a ודאי status, if you knew that the
טבל, tevel, the grain was טבל, tevel, and you have a doubt
that it got changed, did this person take תרומות ומעשרות? terumos u'maasros?
But most of the time he would have. Can you use that
to assume that that has changed the status? So that's in a
way similar to this question of רוב rov. and חזקה, chazaka and
we generally say רוב rov wins, but maybe it wins, but maybe
it's not ודאי. Maybe that's the point. When רוב rov wins there,
we're still going to be concerned about the possibility otherwise. We generally
go by the רוב, rov but there's always a little bit of
a question. Maybe when it's against a חזקה, chazaka. a question mark
still remains. Like this, it's רוב rov with an asterisk, okay? So
that's...
well, you wouldn't burn the תרומה, terumah and you wouldn't bring the
קרבן on the basis of it and so on. So maybe that's
what we're excluding when it's against a חזקה, chazaka it's not like
a definite. So the גמרא says, ולא שרפינן עלה את התרומה, v'lo
sarfinan alei es ha'terumah, you wouldn't burn תרומה terumah in that case.
If it was a רוב rov against חזקה, chazakah even if you
would rule טמא, it would be טמא with a little question. So
the גמרא says: no. I mean not no, but yes, but we
wouldn't have to say that. והאמר רבי יוחנן חדא זימנא, ve'ha'amar Rabbi
Yochanan chada zimna, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan already laid down that principle
another time. So that presumably would have been what he was saying
here. Where did he lay down the principle? דתנן, ditnan, we taught
in the משנה: תינוק הנמצא בצד העיסה ובצק בידו. tinok hanimtza b'tzad
ha'issah u'vatzek b'yado. You have an infant who was
טמא, whose mother had just given birth, so her mother's a נדה,
touched the infant. The infant is טמא. And there's
dough, and you want to know, did the infant touch the dough?
So there's the dough, there's the infant, and guess what's in the
infant's hand? A little piece of dough. So the question is: did
the infant touch all the rest of the dough? Now, the dough
has a חזקה chazakah of being טהור, tahor right? That was its
prior status. But from the evidence, it's quite clear or seems very
likely that the infant touched the dough. There's another possibility. What's the
other possibility? Someone said: Oh, here, here, have a little piece of
dough. It wasn't the dough. But it's still quite likely. So how
do you treat the dough? That's the question. ובצק בידו, u'vatzek b'yado,
and he has a little piece of dough. רבי מאיר מטהר, Rabbi
Meir metaher, the dough is טהור. tahor You go by חזקה. chazakah
Forget about the possibility the infant touched it. וחכמים מטמאין, ve'chachamim metamin,
and חכמים Chachamim say: no, the dough is טמא. שדרכו של תינוק
לטפח, she'darko shel tinok l'tape'ach,
that the way of a תינוק tinok is to לטפח, l'tape'ach, which
is טפח, tefach, a hand, to touch everything. So we can assume
that he touched the dough if he has dough in his hand.
מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir? Now,
how could רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir ignore that רוב? rov Normally we
say רוב rov wins out. How does he ignore it? קסבר: kasavar:
רוב תינוקות מטפחים, rov tinokos metap'chim, fine, I concede, most infants sort
of pat around. ומיעוט אין מטפחים, u'miyut ein metap'chim, but there's a
minority that wouldn't have touched the dough, that don't go around exploring
like that. ועיסה זו בחזקת טהרה עומדת. ve'issah zu b'chezkat taharah omedes.
This dough had a prior status, a חזקה chazakah of being
טהור. וניעטמיך מיעוטו לחזקה. v'ne'etzmech miyuto l'chazaka. Combine the minority possibility that
this is not one of those infants that goes patting around with
the status quo of the dough. ואיתר ליה רוב. v'isar lei rov.
It's two against one. Here you have the status quo and you
don't have a definite against it. You have a majority, but there's
a minority possibility that it retains its status quo. That minority possibility
confirms the status quo or allows us to maintain the status quo
and not override it with a רוב. rov Now, this is important
because, as Michael said, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is known throughout ש"ס
as being חושש למיעוטא, choshesh l'miyuta, concerning for minority possibilities. Normally when
you read that, that just sounds like רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir a
מחמיר. machmir. Every time there's a little possibility, I don't want to
assume it's okay, there's a tiny possibility it might not be, we
have to be concerned, we have
to be safe. Here you see that it's not really that. Here
you see that it's more of a principled approach, which is: if
there's a minority possibility, I cannot ignore it. So normally I can't
ignore it, I have to be concerned about it. But what if
the minority possibility actually makes something מותר? muttar? So I also am
not going to ignore it. So I have a status quo. I'm
not going to say the תינוק tinok definitely touched. There's a minority
possibility that cannot be ignored that the infant did not touch. And
because I don't ignore minority possibilities, I will allow me to continue
with the status quo and say that the dough is טהור. That's
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. Yes.
I just have a question. If a נדה touches, or a woman
who is not טהור touches a child, how does the child become
טהור again?
Dunk in a מקוה. mikvah.
The child would have to go to a מקוה? mikvah?
Yeah, if you want. I mean, he only needs to be טהור
if he's going to touch תרומה terumah and so on. But it's
true, in a house of כהנים, kohanim, it's a good question. In
a house of כהנים... kohanim... how would they keep the infants away
from I guess through dunking the kids in a מקווה mikvah I
don't know I like that but the woman the mother look the
mother is only a נידה niddah is only a טמאה tmeiah as
a יולדת yoledes for a week or two weeks and then afterwards
she's not and then if she's nursing she's not going to become
a נידה niddah most likely for two years after she's nursing
so it would be a very limited problem not
only the mother the father doesn't touch the child yeah what do
you mean if it's in the house you mean
if it's a כהן Kohen house that you have to worry about
תרומה terumah fine oh so during that week
that's
an interesting question so maybe during that first week nobody
touches the child no
the child doesn't touch a person right that's true the child is
only a ראשון rishon that's the point thank you thank you the
child is only a ראשון rishon okay that's a good point child's
only a ראשון rishon so if you touch the child as a
person you're not טמא we can't
go through all this
right now so fine back to the גמרא so now it's just
the point about yeah let's focus people I want to get to
the משנה we can get to the משנה if we focus okay
so right
a ראשון rishon right only טמא person can become טמא if he
touches a source of טומאה not something that is derivative okay so
now רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir parenthetical רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says טהור
we're not interested in רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir we're interested in the
חכמים Chachamim. that go by the majority and say טמא is it
טמא definite or is it טמא doubtful how much does against חזקה
chazakah is it considered as definite so that's the point רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir was parenthetical רבנן Rabbanan what do the rabbis say מיעוטא
כמאן דליתא דמי miuta keman d'leisa dami ignore the minority we don't
pay attention to it at all ורובא חזקה veruba chazakah so it's
just majority against חזקה chazakah minority doesn't play a role here רובא
עדיף ruba adif רוב rov wins okay now the next question is
how much does רוב rov win is it are you assume definite
טמא or doubtful טמא so that's the debate of ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan when רוב rov wins against חזקה
chazakah דאמר ריש לקיש משום רבי יאשיה d'amar Reish Lakish mishum Rebbi
Yoshiyah זו היא חזקה ששורפין עליה את התרומה zu hi chazakah shesorfin
aleha es haterumah this is a חזקה chazakah that not just go
against you wouldn't go against this חזקה chazakah you go by the
רוב rov and you would actually burn תרומה even when it's a
רוב rov against חזקה chazakah you go by the רוב rov you
assume the dough is טמא and if that dough was תרומה you
would burn it you assume definitely טמא ורבי יוחנן אומר אין זו
חזקה ששורפין עליה את התרומה v'Rebbi Yochanan omer ein zu chazakah shesorfin
aleha es haterumah no
I am sorry it is not strong enough to say you burn
the dough is טמא but you would wait for it to rot
it is it is טמא out of a doubt not definite because
it worked against a חזקה chazakah so now we actually find out
an interesting thing when רוב rov goes against חזקה chazakah. רוב rov,
wins but only with an asterisk רוב rov. question mark okay so
therefore when when we said רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan said three times
רוב הוא ודאי rov hu vadai what's he excluding if you wanted
to exclude when רוב rov? goes against חזקה chazakah, well actually that'd
be true he would be excluding that case but the גמרא assumes
you don't bother repeating yourself I mean the funny assumption the גמרא
makes so no he wouldn't bother going out of the way we
already told us that we know רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan holds רוב
against חזקה it's not ודאי that's not the point here so what
is the point so the גמרא says אלא למיעוטי רובא דרבי יהודה
ela l'miyuti ruba d'Rebbi Yehuda to exclude the case of רוב of
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda what's רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda case דתנן המפלת
חתיכה disnan hamapeles chatichah a woman miscarries against some type of a
chunk something that you don't know it is would not make her
a יולדת yoledes it's totally misformed it's not considered sufficiently you know
it's formed or not sufficiently it's not naturally enough normally formed that
it makes her considered to be a woman who a יולדת yoledes
child a woman who has given birth and has that טומאה so
she is not a יולדת yoledes now the question is fine she's
not a יולדת but do we assume that there was also blood
that came out with it and she's a נידה niddah okay because
uterine blood came out now if she saw uterine blood the answer
is obvious then she would be a נידה niddah but you didn't
see uterine blood so let's take a look אם יש עמה דם
im yesh imah dam if she saw the blood טמאה tmeiah then
she's then forget יולדת she's טמאה tmeiah, she's a נידה niddah ואם
לאו v'im lav and if not טהורה tehorah she's טהורה tehorah because
there's no blood רבי יהודה אומר בין כך ובין כך טמאה Rebbi
Yehuda omer bein kach u'vein kach tmeiah either way she's טמאה tmeiah,
why because actually one thing you could say is that there definitely
was blood it got lost and that's the discussion the גמרא has
elsewhere that whenever something comes out of the uterus you assume it
brings blood with it but actually that's not what רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda says רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda actually says that the חתיכה chatichah
this chunk is probably some type of congealed blood okay it's not
a huge chunk דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל d'amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel and now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of
שמואל לא טימא רבי יהודה אלא בחתיכה של ארבעה מיני דמים lo
tima Rebbi Yehuda ela b'chatichah shel arba'ah minei damim it's only when
this little chunk whatever had the colors of blood there are four
colors of red that are considered נידה niddah blood if it had
one of those four red colors then it is טמאה because then
you assume that it is actually congealed dried blood and not some
type of a you know misformed fetus אבל שאר מיני דמים aval
shear minei damim or other colors even if they're not the red
colors that that make blood טמא טהורה tehorah so basically why if
it has these types of problematic red colors he is going to
say I am going to assume that this is blood that is
congealed רבי יוחנן אמר Rebbi Yochanan amar and רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
says של ארבעה מיני דמים shel arba'ah minei damim if it has
those red colors דברי הכל טמאה divrei hakol tmeiah everybody would say
it's congealed blood I mean it has the red colors ושל שאר
דמים v'shel shear damim if it has other colors colors of non-טמא
blood, it's a funny thing, you would have said other colors, but
it means, that's what it means, if it has greenish, yellowish, other
types of colors, not the red colors that are
problematic. Everybody would say it's not a problem. Okay, if it has
problematic colors it is, if it doesn't have problematic colors it isn't,
so what's the debate? We don't know. So לא נחלקו אלא כשהפילה
ושנתפררה ואינה יודעת מה הפילה. Lo nechelku ela keshepila veshanitparara ve'eina yoda'at
mah hipila.
She didn't look at the chunk, okay? A chunk came out of
her body and she didn't get a chance to look at it.
Right, she was walking through a river. רבי יהודה סבר, Rabbi Yehuda
savar, זיל בתר רוב חתיכות. zil batar rov chatichot. You go by
most types of like things that come, discharges from a woman's body,
especially like the congealed chunk. ורוב חתיכות של ארבעה מיני דמים הוויין,
Verov chatichot shel arba minei damin havyan, and generally they would tend
to be of the red colors so you assume that it was
red and blood and that she was and that she is a
נדה. ורבנן סברי, Verabbanan savri, זיל בתר רוב חתיכות לא אמרינן. zil
batar rov chatichot lo amrinan. We don't go by the majority. Now
here's a question. What is the debate first of all of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the רבנן? Rabbanan? Maybe they don't agree to
his analysis of reality. They don't think that most things are, have
those red colors. Or maybe they agree they do, but they would
say it doesn't change her status. Why would it not change her
status? Because even if there's a majority, she still has a חזקה
of being טהורה. tehorah. So maybe again it's the question of רוב
against חזקה. Nevertheless, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said we assume it's blood,
we assume she's a נדה, she is טמאה, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is coming to say even when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
she's טמאה, there is not ודאי, it is still ספק, or maybe
he's going even further because saying רוב and ספק, that's what we
said before, when רוב is against a חזקה, it's ספק. So maybe
he's going even further and he's saying we don't rule like רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. In that case we don't go by רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda רוב, we go by the חכמים. Chachamim I want to
emphasize three cases by women and טומאה וטהרה we go by the
רוב. There's another debate, do we go by רוב? And there we
don't. There we go like the חכמים and we say that the
woman is טהורה, tehorah, and with that we have caught up and
we will end for today.
Two minutes early. And...